<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Hugo Cisneros - Personal page</title>
    <link>https://hugocisneros.com/projects/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Hugo Cisneros - Personal page</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 14:24:46 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugocisneros.com/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Posos Challenge</title>
      <link>https://hugocisneros.com/projects/posos_dl/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2019 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hugocisneros.com/projects/posos_dl/</guid>
      <description>Links  Project slides PDF project report  Description This project was part of the course Theoretical deep learning (L&amp;rsquo;apprentissage par réseaux de neurones profonds, taught in French) by Stéphane Mallat at Collège de France.
This course was composed of theoretical lectures and a machine learning challenge.
I worked on an intent prediction problem for drug-related question, proposed by the healthcare startup Posos. The goal was to classify real user questions into one of 52 classes representing the type of drug-related information they are looking for.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graph neural networks for influence maximization</title>
      <link>https://hugocisneros.com/projects/graph_nn_for_influence_maximization/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2019 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hugocisneros.com/projects/graph_nn_for_influence_maximization/</guid>
      <description>Links  Project slides PDF project report  Description This project was part of the course Graphs in Machine learning taught by Michal Valko. The project was proposed by Peter Battaglia and supervised by Peter and Michal together.
The goal of this project was to apply graph neural networks on the influence maximization (IM) problem for a graph with the independent cascade (IC) assumption (more details in the report).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic optimization for large scale optimal transport</title>
      <link>https://hugocisneros.com/projects/stochastic_optimization_for_large_scale_optimal_transport/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2019 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hugocisneros.com/projects/stochastic_optimization_for_large_scale_optimal_transport/</guid>
      <description>Links  Project slides PDF project report Github  Description This project was part of the course Mathematical Foundations Of Data Science taught by Gabriel Peyré in 2019.
The goal was to reproduce and extend results from [1] to other algorithms, including SAGA [2]. After comparing the regularized optimal transport convergence results for these algorithms, I studied an optimal school placement and allocation problem in several French regions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
