<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Life on Hugo Cisneros</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/tags/life/</link><description>Recent content in Life on Hugo Cisneros</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2022 14:06:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugocisneros.com/tags/life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Talk: Alife 2020 keynote Sara Walker - The Natural History of Information</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/talk_alife_2020_keynote_sara_walker_the_natural_history_of_information/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2022 14:06:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/talk_alife_2020_keynote_sara_walker_the_natural_history_of_information/</guid><description>tags Life The problem of defining life Definitions of life have always been elusive.
Life does not exist.
&amp;mdash; Andrew Ellington (American Chemical Society 2012).
as one focuses experimentally on any of the &amp;lsquo;defining&amp;rsquo; properties of &amp;rsquo;life&amp;rsquo;, the sharp boundary seems to blur, splitting into finer and finer sub-divisions
&amp;mdash; Jack Szostak (J. Biomolecular Struc. Dyn. 29.4 (2012) : 599-600.)
When looking at matter down to the chemical level, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to tell what is fundamentally different between living and non-living matter.</description></item><item><title>Notes on: The information theory of individuality by Krakauer, D., Bertschinger, N., Olbrich, E., Flack, J. C., &amp; Ay, N. (2020)</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/krakauerinformationtheoryindividuality2020/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 12:46:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/krakauerinformationtheoryindividuality2020/</guid><description>tags Information theory, Life source (Krakauer et al. 2020) Summary This paper introduces an information theoretic definition of individuality for complex systems.
In a few words, the authors idea of individuality is based on the amount of information transmitted through time.
If the information transmitted forward in time is close to maximal, we take that as evidence for individuality.
Formally, a system \(\mathcal{S}\) is considered in interaction with an environment \(\mathcal{E}\).</description></item><item><title>Notes on: An Integrated Perspective on the Constitutive and Interactive Dimensions of Autonomy by Beer, R. D. (2020)</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/beerintegratedperspectiveconstitutive2020/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 09:57:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/beerintegratedperspectiveconstitutive2020/</guid><description>tags Emergence, Life, Cellular automata source (Beer 2020) Summary Constitution: &amp;ldquo;How emergent individuals are put together and maintained&amp;rdquo; Interaction: &amp;ldquo;How emergent individuals as a whole engage with the environment&amp;rdquo;
Use Conway&amp;rsquo;s Game of Life as a toy model where each cell and update rule is like the Physics of the universe and this physics gives rise to a simple chemistry which can in turn support self-sustaining networks of reactions and some form of biology.</description></item><item><title>Article: What Is an Individual? Biology Seeks Clues in Information Theory.</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/what_is_an_individual_biology_seeks_clues_in_information_theory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Aug 2020 09:17:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/what_is_an_individual_biology_seeks_clues_in_information_theory/</guid><description>tags Life resources (Krakauer et al. 2020) source Quanta Magazine “In a way, [biology] is a science of individuality,” said Melanie Mitchell, a computer scientist at the Santa Fe Institute.
And yet, the notion of what it means to be an individual often gets glossed over. “So far we have a concept of ‘individual’ that’s very much like the concept of ‘pile,’” said Maxwell Ramstead, a postdoctoral researcher at McGill University.</description></item><item><title>Talk: Alife 2020 keynote Lee Cronin - A Top Down Chemically Embodied Artificial Life Computation</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/talk_alife_2020_keynote_lee_cronin_a_top_down_chemically_embodied_artificial_life_computation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 14:24:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/talk_alife_2020_keynote_lee_cronin_a_top_down_chemically_embodied_artificial_life_computation/</guid><description>tags Life, ALife 2020 Complex molecules are bio-signatures, they are the sign of complex (evolutionary?) processes that have been going on.
Assembly theory Exploring complexity: Lee is showing some theoretical idea about a complexity metric. Like many other metrics, he starts from the observation that neither entropy nor Kolmogorov complexity are suitable for considering the history of an object.
Instead of thinking in terms of disorder or complexity, why not ask simply about &amp;ldquo;how has this object been assembled?</description></item><item><title>Autopoiesis</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/autopoiesis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 21:35:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/autopoiesis/</guid><description> tags Life</description></item><item><title>Evolution</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/evolution/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2020 10:22:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/evolution/</guid><description> tags Artificial life, Life</description></item></channel></rss>