<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hugo Cisneros - Personal page</title>
    <link>https://hugocisneros.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Hugo Cisneros - Personal page</description>
    
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Aug 2021 15:25:56 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://hugocisneros.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Open-ended creation of hybrid creatures with Neural Cellular Automata</title>
      <link>https://hugocisneros.com/blog/2021/08/open-ended-creation-of-hybrid-creatures-with-neural-cellular-automata/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Aug 2021 15:25:56 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://hugocisneros.com/blog/2021/08/open-ended-creation-of-hybrid-creatures-with-neural-cellular-automata/</guid>
      <description>This post describes my submission to the Minecraft Open-endedness challenge 2021. The submission was evaluated with the video below and the code here. This post will detail the methods and tools used for the submission and give hints for future work.
If you want a quick description of the work, have a look at the video:
 Introduction Motivation My current research deals with evolution in complex systems and specifically cellular automata (CA).</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>My Org-roam Notes Workflow</title>
      <link>https://hugocisneros.com/blog/2021/06/my-org-roam-notes-workflow/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 13:40:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://hugocisneros.com/blog/2021/06/my-org-roam-notes-workflow/</guid>
      <description>Some people expressed interest in my org-roam notes workflow. Setting this up has been an interesting project, teaching me about Emacs, org-mode and a little about web frontend. This post will describe my current workflow in as much details as possible.
Hopefully, you&amp;rsquo;ll learn to create an automated build script to publish your notes on the web and convert your org-roam note network into a graph like the one below.</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Elegance of Optimal Transport</title>
      <link>https://hugocisneros.com/blog/2019/12/the-elegance-of-optimal-transport/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Dec 2019 23:20:20 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://hugocisneros.com/blog/2019/12/the-elegance-of-optimal-transport/</guid>
      <description>This post was largely inspired by Gabriel Peyré and Marco Cuturi&amp;rsquo;s excellent book about Computational Optimal Transport, which is free, (arXiv link, ref: [1]).
A simple problem? Let&amp;rsquo;s start at the beginning: what is Optimal transport (OT)?
It all begins with Gaspard Monge, reading his mémoire [2] in front of eminent scientists and engineers of the time &amp;mdash; including famous Enlightenment philosopher Condorcet &amp;mdash; at the French Académie Royale des Sciences in 1776.</description>
    </item>
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
