<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Language on Hugo Cisneros</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/tags/language/</link><description>Recent content in Language on Hugo Cisneros</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 10:04:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugocisneros.com/tags/language/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Unker non-linear writing system</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/unker_non_linear_writing_system/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 10:04:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/unker_non_linear_writing_system/</guid><description>tags Language resources https://s.ai/nlws/ A fascinating writing system based on glyphs connected to each other to create meaning. The system is quite advanced and reading its grammar is like discovering some new alien language. It was created by Alex Fink and Sai in 2010.
This is the kind of complexity that would be incredible to discover in open-ended evolving language systems. A system starting from elementary components and no particular assumption about what language should be, could come up with such exotic models (probably even more exotic in the case of a truly open-ended system).</description></item><item><title>NLP</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/nlp/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 09:15:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/nlp/</guid><description> tags Machine learning, Language NLP is about creating algorithms that can manipulate and use language. It is often thought that having functioning NLP algorithms that provably &amp;ldquo;understand&amp;rdquo; language would be equivalent to reaching human-level Artificial Intelligence.
Tasks Language modeling Text classification Question answering Data manipulation There are several ways to encode text data.
One-hot encoding of characters One-hot encoding of words Byte-pair encoding which can be seen as being a compromise between the two</description></item></channel></rss>