<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Artificial Intelligence on Hugo Cisneros</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/tags/artificial-intelligence/</link><description>Recent content in Artificial Intelligence on Hugo Cisneros</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2022 19:28:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugocisneros.com/tags/artificial-intelligence/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Cellular automata</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/cellular_automata/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2022 19:28:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/cellular_automata/</guid><description>tags Emergence, Chaos, Artificial Intelligence resources Wikipedia, (Von Neumann, Burks 1966; Wolfram 2002) Definition A cellular automaton is a computational model defined with respect to a regular grid of individual elements (called cells). Each of those cells can be in one of a finite number of states &amp;mdash; alive or dead, \(\{1, 2, 3\}\), etc.
A cellular automaton&amp;rsquo;s evolution is simulated in discrete timesteps. At each new timestep, cells are updated according to a local evolution rule.</description></item><item><title>Automation</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/automation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2022 13:01:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/automation/</guid><description> tags Economics, Artificial Intelligence Labor and automation resources Interview with Juan Sebastian Carbonell</description></item><item><title>Notes on: One model for the learning of language by Yang, Y., &amp; Piantadosi, S. T. (2022)</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/yangonemodellearning2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 13:55:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/yangonemodellearning2022/</guid><description>source (Yang, Piantadosi 2022) tags NLP, Artificial Intelligence, Machine learning Summary This paper introduces a model for learning language from few examples while generalizing effectively.
This model builds sentences with function that are combinations of elementary functions, including:
pair(L, C) : Concatenates character C onto list L first(L) : Return the first character of L flip(P) : Return true with probability P if(B, X, Y) : Return X if B else return Y (X and Y may be lists, sets, or probabilities) etc.</description></item><item><title>Machine learning</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/machine_learning/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Aug 2021 21:45:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/machine_learning/</guid><description>tags Artificial Intelligence, Applied maths Machine learning is about constructing algorithms that can approximate complex functions from observations of input/output pairs. Machine learning is related to Statistics since its goal is to make predictions based on data.
Examples of such functions include:
Image classification Time-series prediction Language modeling Regression The goal is to approximate a target function \(f\) or signal \(S\).</description></item><item><title>Notes on: AI-GAs: AI-generating algorithms, an alternate paradigm for producing general artificial intelligence by Clune, J. (2019)</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/cluneaigasaigeneratingalgorithms2019/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 11:13:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/cluneaigasaigeneratingalgorithms2019/</guid><description>tags Artificial Intelligence, Genetic algorithms, Open-ended Evolution source (Clune 2019) Summary Nowadays, the design of AI systems is approached through one main way (more or less): the implementation of some elementary building blocks &amp;mdash; like convolutions, skip connections, activation functions, attention, etc. We currently have no clear idea how to combine these relatively successful blocks into a global system that would take advantage of each and every one of them.</description></item><item><title>Open-ended Evolution</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/open_ended_evolution/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 14:56:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/open_ended_evolution/</guid><description>tags Evolution, Complexity, Artificial Intelligence resources Open-endedness: The last grand challenge you’ve never heard of My idea of Open Ended evolution thoughtsopen-ended-evolution As part of my research, I have been thinking a lot about open-ended evolution and what this concept means to me. Although it is still early in my research journey, I will go into the process of writing down my thoughts about this very challenging concept in order to have material on which I will be able to reflect later and understand how my beliefs have changed.</description></item><item><title>The Bitter Lesson</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/the_bitter_lesson/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 10:35:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/the_bitter_lesson/</guid><description>tags Machine learning, Artificial Intelligence author Richard Sutton resources Link The Bitter Lesson is a pattern that can be observed in several areas of machine learning: many hard problems involving some form of artificial intelligence have seen dramatic progress at some point in the last 50 years, which was mostly driven by data and computations as opposed to &amp;ldquo;clever&amp;rdquo; human engineering.
If this trend is a fundamental principle (which is what the article argues) it would mean that most of the time spent on engineering features and task-specific representations is wasted.</description></item><item><title>Notes on: Intelligence without representation by Brooks, R. A. (1991)</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/brooksintelligencerepresentation1991/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Mar 2021 14:35:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/brooksintelligencerepresentation1991/</guid><description>tags Artificial Intelligence source (Brooks 1991) Summary What is intelligence Intelligence cannot be thought of as a collection of building blocks that may one fall into place to form a coherent whole.
The authors argue for another approach to build artificially intelligent systems:
Build the systems incrementally, with complete systems each step of the way to ensure that the pieces and their interfaces are valid. Build intelligent systems at each step of the way that should be let loose in the real world with real sensing and action.</description></item><item><title>Notes on: Climbing towards NLU: On Meaning, Form, and Understanding in the Age of Data by Bender, E. M., &amp; Koller, A. (2020)</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/benderclimbingnlumeaning2020/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 09:57:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/benderclimbingnlumeaning2020/</guid><description>source (Bender, Koller 2020) tags NLP, Artificial Intelligence, Evaluating NLP Summary The main point of the article could be summarized like so:
We argue that the language modeling task, because it only uses form as training data, cannot in principle lead to learning of meaning. We take the term language model to refer to any system trained only on the task of string prediction, whether it operates over characters, words or sentences, and sequentially or not.</description></item><item><title>Why programming is a good medium for expressing poorly understood and sloppily-formulated ideas</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/why_programming_is_a_good_medium/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Mar 2021 10:17:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/why_programming_is_a_good_medium/</guid><description>source Link tags Artificial Intelligence, Coding author Marvin Minsky What can computers do? The fallacy under discussion is the widespread superstition that we can&amp;rsquo;t write a computer program to do something unless one has an extremely clear, precise formulation of what is to be done, and exactly how to do it.
It is generally believed that computer programs cannot be more than a set of rules and instructions for what to do in a given computer state.</description></item><item><title>Neuroscience</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/neuroscience/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 15:58:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/neuroscience/</guid><description> tags Biological life, Artificial Intelligence</description></item><item><title>Alan Turing</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/alan_turing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 08:06:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/alan_turing/</guid><description> tags Computer science, Artificial Intelligence, Cryptography</description></item><item><title>Robotics</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/robotics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2020 22:59:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/robotics/</guid><description> tags Artificial life, Artificial Intelligence</description></item><item><title>Artificial intelligence test</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/artificial_intelligence_test/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2020 10:56:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/artificial_intelligence_test/</guid><description>tags Artificial Intelligence The most famous example is the Turing test.</description></item><item><title>Article: Open-endedness: The last grand challenge you’ve never heard of</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/open_endedness_the_last_grand_challenge_you_ve_never_heard_of/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Aug 2020 12:09:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/open_endedness_the_last_grand_challenge_you_ve_never_heard_of/</guid><description> authors Kenneth Stanley tags Artificial Intelligence, Open-ended Evolution source Link</description></item></channel></rss>