<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Signal processing on Hugo Cisneros</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/tags/signal-processing/</link><description>Recent content in Signal processing on Hugo Cisneros</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 16:07:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugocisneros.com/tags/signal-processing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Compressed sensing</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/compressed_sensing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 16:07:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/compressed_sensing/</guid><description>tags Signal processing resources (Candes et al. 2006) Description Compressed sensing is a technique to recover a sparse signal from partial observations.
The signal is described as a $N$-dimensional vector \(\textbf{s}\). We make \(M\) measurements, where a measurements means a projection of the signal \(\textbf{s}\) onto some known vector. The result of all these measurements can be written as \(\textbf{y} = \textbf{Fs}\), where \(\textbf{F}\) is a \(M \times N\) matrix.</description></item><item><title>Wavelets</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/wavelets/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2020 09:23:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/wavelets/</guid><description> tags Applied maths, Signal processing Wavelets are functions with specific properties that make them useful when dealing with images. They are used for lossy image compression.
Types of wavelets Haar wavelets Daubechies wavelets</description></item><item><title>Image processing</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/image_processing/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Nov 2020 09:17:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/image_processing/</guid><description>tags Applied maths, Signal processing Scale an image with no interpolation Imagemagick documentation
convert source.[png|gif|...] -scale 400% target.[png|gif|...] The scale option can also take integer parameters (without the percent sign) to indicate the target size.
Remove metadata from an image Useful for preserving Online privacy when publishing images. Pictures taken with smartphones and other modern devices often contain large amounts of data about location, time and date and device type.</description></item></channel></rss>