<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Emergence on Hugo Cisneros</title>
    <link>https://hugocisneros.com/tags/emergence/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Emergence on Hugo Cisneros</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 09:05:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugocisneros.com/tags/emergence/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Cellular automata</title>
      <link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/cellular_automata/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 09:05:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/cellular_automata/</guid>
      <description>tags Emergence, Chaos, Artificial Intelligence resources Wikipedia, (Von Neumann and Burks 1966; Wolfram 2002)  Definition A cellular automaton is a computational model defined with respect to a regular grid of individual elements (called cells). Each of those cells can be in one of a finite number of states &amp;mdash; alive or dead, \(\{1, 2, 3\}\), etc.
A cellular automaton&amp;rsquo;s evolution is simulated in discrete timesteps. At each new timestep, cells are updated according to a local evolution rule.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on: Emergence in artificial life by Gershenson, C. (2021)</title>
      <link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/gershensonemergenceartificiallife2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 10:45:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/gershensonemergenceartificiallife2021/</guid>
      <description>tags Artificial life, Emergence source (Gershenson 2021)  Summary The paper introduces a complexity metric based on information. emergence is first measured with Shannon&amp;rsquo;s information: \[E = - K \sum_{i} p_i \log p_i\]
Then the author argues that self-organization can be seen as the opposite of emergence, and measured with \[S = 1 - E\]
 [&amp;hellip;] complex systems tend to exhibit both emergence and self-organization. Extreme emergence implies chaos, while extreme self-organization implies immutability.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emergence in artificial life</title>
      <link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/emergence_in_artificial_life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 May 2021 14:23:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/emergence_in_artificial_life/</guid>
      <description> tags Artificial life, Emergence resources (Gershenson 2021)  Bibliography Gershenson, Carlos. April 30, 2021. &#34;Emergence in Artificial Life&#34;. Arxiv:2105.03216 [physics]. http://arxiv.org/abs/2105.03216.&amp;nbsp;See notes  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on: An Integrated Perspective on the Constitutive and Interactive Dimensions of Autonomy by Beer, R. D. (2020)</title>
      <link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/beerintegratedperspectiveconstitutive2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 09:57:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/beerintegratedperspectiveconstitutive2020/</guid>
      <description>tags Emergence, Life, Cellular automata source (Beer 2020)  Summary Constitution: &amp;ldquo;How emergent individuals are put together and maintained&amp;rdquo; Interaction: &amp;ldquo;How emergent individuals as a whole engage with the environment&amp;rdquo;
Use Conway&amp;rsquo;s Game of Life as a toy model where each cell and update rule is like the Physics of the universe and this physics gives rise to a simple chemistry which can in turn support self-sustaining networks of reactions and some form of biology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk: Alife 2020 keynote Michael Levin - Robot Cancer</title>
      <link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/talk_alife_2020_keynote_michael_levin_robot_cancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 18:42:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/talk_alife_2020_keynote_michael_levin_robot_cancer/</guid>
      <description>tags Emergence, Biological life, ALife 2020  How do organisms store information and are able to pass it down through very profound structural changes (from a caterpillar to a butterfly, when cutting a flatworm in multiple pieces, etc.)?
Embryogenesis is a reliable self-assembly. It relies on stem cell differentiation but that&amp;rsquo;s not enough: some tumor (Teratoma) are differentiated but don&amp;rsquo;t have the right 3D spatial organisation.
Where is the large-scale pattern specified?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
