<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Philosophy on Hugo Cisneros</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/tags/philosophy/</link><description>Recent content in Philosophy on Hugo Cisneros</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2022 10:39:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugocisneros.com/tags/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Consciousness</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/consciousness/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2022 10:39:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/consciousness/</guid><description> tags Philosophy</description></item><item><title>Reductionism</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/reductionism/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Sep 2021 15:14:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/reductionism/</guid><description>tags Philosophy, Physics Reductionism is a philosophy according to which the laws of physics are relatively simple and could be expressed concisely. If we were to understand and model all those laws we could explain any given phenomenon by breaking it down into its smaller parts until we just need to apply these simple laws.
With the current state of physics, it seems we are close to understanding many of these fundamental laws (although major shortcomings remain in the theory).</description></item><item><title>Zuse's thesis</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/zuse_s_thesis/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 09:58:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/zuse_s_thesis/</guid><description>tags Physics, Philosophy resources Juergen Schmidhuber&amp;rsquo;s page, (Schmidhuber 1999) Zuse&amp;rsquo;s thesis is the idea that the Universe could be running within a digital computer. It was formulated by Konrad Zuse in Rechnender Raum (Calculating Space) in 1969. The computer could be a very large Cellular automaton according to Zuse.
A computer program to simulate our Universe (and all the others) Systematically create and execute all programs for a universal computer, such as a Turing machine or a CA; the first program is run for one instruction every second step on average, the next for one instruction every second of the remaining steps on average, and so on.</description></item><item><title>Notes on: More Is Different by Anderson, P. W. (1972)</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/andersonmoredifferent1972/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 May 2021 14:37:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/andersonmoredifferent1972/</guid><description>tags Complexity, Philosophy source (Anderson 1972) This is a fundamental paper discussing the fundamental laws of Physics and their relations with complexity.
Reductionism doesn&amp;rsquo;t imply constructionism It is generally accepted that the fundamental laws governing our Universe are relatively simple. We feel we understand many of these laws quite well. However, understanding these fundamental laws are far from enough to actually describe and reconstruct all phenomena we witness.</description></item><item><title>The Simulated reality hypothesis</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/the_simulated_reality_hypothesis/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jul 2020 21:27:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/the_simulated_reality_hypothesis/</guid><description>tags Philosophy The simulation argument Nick Bostrom proposed a trilemma in 2003:
&amp;ldquo;The fraction of human-level civilizations that reach a posthuman stage (that is, one capable of running high-fidelity ancestor simulations) is very close to zero&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;The fraction of posthuman civilizations that are interested in running simulations of their evolutionary history, or variations thereof, is very close to zero&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;The fraction of all people with our kind of experiences that are living in a simulation is very close to one.</description></item><item><title>Nick Bostrom</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/nick_bostrom/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jul 2020 21:25:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/nick_bostrom/</guid><description> tags Philosophy</description></item></channel></rss>