<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>ALife 2020 on Hugo Cisneros</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/tags/alife-2020/</link><description>Recent content in ALife 2020 on Hugo Cisneros</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 17:30:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugocisneros.com/tags/alife-2020/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Talk: Alife 2020 keynote Luis Zaman - New Frontiers in Alife: What was old is new again</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/talk_alife_2020_keynote_luis_zaman_new_frontiers_in_alife_what_was_old_is_new_again/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 17:30:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/talk_alife_2020_keynote_luis_zaman_new_frontiers_in_alife_what_was_old_is_new_again/</guid><description>tags Artificial life, ALife 2020 This keynote is about this sub-community of ALife which is dedicated to constructing actual artificial systems that can exhibit Open-ended Evolution, and Life-like behavior.
The first models that tried to construct ALife were probably Von Neumann&amp;rsquo;s self-reproducing CA and Langton&amp;rsquo;s loop. However, their main limitation was they were extremely brittle, which is why evolution did not really work in them.
Zaman&amp;rsquo;s definition of evolution is</description></item><item><title>Notes on: A model of urban evolution based on innovation diffusion by Raimbault, J. (2020)</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/raimbaultmodelurbanevolution2020/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 09:58:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/raimbaultmodelurbanevolution2020/</guid><description>source (Raimbault 2020) tags ALife 2020, Complex Systems, Evolution, Urban science Summary This paper studies the concept of innovation diffusion and how this could be seen as a way cities evolve.
Modeling this enables finding that global integration of cities (fully connected city graph on a territory) is not optimal for efficiently diffusing innovation that can spontaneously appear in any city.
I am interested in taking an ALife inspired approach to studying cities, as it can show cities as they could be.</description></item><item><title>Notes on: Fast and stable MAP-Elites in noisy domains using deep grids by Flageat, M., &amp; Cully, A. (2020)</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/flageatfaststablemapelites2020/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 09:57:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/flageatfaststablemapelites2020/</guid><description>source (Flageat and Cully 2020) tags ALife 2020, MAP-Elites, Quality diversity Summary MAP-Elites can be problematic in face of uncertainty because:
individuals can be unexpectedly lucky the behavior space can be hard to estimate and result in misplacing individuals. Some mitigation techniques have been explored, e.g in (Justesen, Risiand Mouret 2019) and this paper is about introducing another way of dealing with noisy domains without using sampling.</description></item><item><title>Notes on: Resilient Life: An Exploration of Perturbed Autopoietic Patterns in Conway's Game of Life by Cika, A., Cohen, E., Kruszewski, G., Seet, L., Steinmann, P., &amp; Yin, W. (2020)</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/cikaresilientlifeexploration2020/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 09:57:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/cikaresilientlifeexploration2020/</guid><description>tags ALife 2020, Cellular automata, Autopoiesis source (Cika et al. 2020) Summary This paper is about the possible resistance of GoL patterns to perturbations and the structures that could enable this to happen. They also want to know if resilience is a universal property of computational systems.
They test two types of resilience:
Additive (add one or two live cells to the pattern) Negative (&amp;ldquo;kill&amp;rdquo; one or two live cells from the pattern) They use 3 metrics for resilience:</description></item><item><title>Talk: Alife 2020 keynote Lee Cronin - A Top Down Chemically Embodied Artificial Life Computation</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/talk_alife_2020_keynote_lee_cronin_a_top_down_chemically_embodied_artificial_life_computation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 14:24:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/talk_alife_2020_keynote_lee_cronin_a_top_down_chemically_embodied_artificial_life_computation/</guid><description>tags Life, ALife 2020 Complex molecules are bio-signatures, they are the sign of complex (evolutionary?) processes that have been going on.
Assembly theory Exploring complexity: Lee is showing some theoretical idea about a complexity metric. Like many other metrics, he starts from the observation that neither entropy nor Kolmogorov complexity are suitable for considering the history of an object.
Instead of thinking in terms of disorder or complexity, why not ask simply about &amp;ldquo;how has this object been assembled?</description></item><item><title>Talk: Alife 2020 keynote Michael Levin - Robot Cancer</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/talk_alife_2020_keynote_michael_levin_robot_cancer/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 18:42:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/talk_alife_2020_keynote_michael_levin_robot_cancer/</guid><description>tags Emergence, Biological life, ALife 2020 How do organisms store information and are able to pass it down through very profound structural changes (from a caterpillar to a butterfly, when cutting a flatworm in multiple pieces, etc.)?
Embryogenesis is a reliable self-assembly. It relies on stem cell differentiation but that&amp;rsquo;s not enough: some tumor (Teratoma) are differentiated but don&amp;rsquo;t have the right 3D spatial organisation.
Where is the large-scale pattern specified?</description></item></channel></rss>