<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Climate on Hugo Cisneros</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/tags/climate/</link><description>Recent content in Climate on Hugo Cisneros</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2023 11:03:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugocisneros.com/tags/climate/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Energy</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/energy/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2023 11:03:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/energy/</guid><description> tags Climate Renewable energy Non-renewable energy</description></item><item><title>Carbon emissions</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/carbon_emissions/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 16:28:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/carbon_emissions/</guid><description>tags Climate Scopes of carbon emissions Usually, greenhouse gas emissions are divided into multiple categories that correspond to different scopes of involvement in the emissions. An entity is responsible for all these emissions, but it may have different levels of control on the various scopes.
Scope 1: Direct emissions This is the CO2 or other greenhouse gas (GHG) the organization emits directly. Examples: Direct fossil fuel burning, methane leak, etc.</description></item><item><title>Carbon capture</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/carbon_capture/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 16:20:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/carbon_capture/</guid><description>tags Climate, Carbon emissions Carbon capture consists in using devices to re-capture and store some the carbon emissions emitted in the past or that will be emitted in the near future.
Carbon capture will be too expensive for too little results ‘Carbon Capture’ Is No Fix. Big Oil’s Known for Decades &amp;mdash; The Tyee, 7 July 2022</description></item><item><title>Carbon offsetting</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/carbon_offsetting/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 16:18:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/carbon_offsetting/</guid><description> tags Climate, Carbon emissions The Carbon Con, an article from Source Material
Bibliography</description></item><item><title>Carbon tax</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/carbon_tax/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 16:18:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/carbon_tax/</guid><description>tags Climate, Economic liberalism, Taxation The idea behind the carbon tax is to tax carbon emissions from private entities, public institutions or individual so as to create an economic incentive for emitting less carbon dioxyde.
Carbon tax and redistribution Perception and public opinion Slides by Mathild Mus (in french)</description></item><item><title>Batteries</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/batteries/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2022 21:07:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/batteries/</guid><description>tags Climate, Energy Gigafactories The word gigafactory was coined by Tesla, who started building its first massive factory in 2014 in Nevada. The word corresponds to the scale of the output of these factories which is on the order of GWh of total battery capacity constructed per year. Now the word is used for all battery factories.
According to a study by Ultimate Media and ABB, the global battery production was 450 GWh in 2020.</description></item><item><title>Extractivism</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/extractivism/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 21:44:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/extractivism/</guid><description>tags Climate, Economics From (Chagnon et al. 2022), a piece on extractivism as a concept and its relation to globalization:
Extractivism as a concept forms a complex ensemble of self-reinforcing practices, mentalities, and power differentials underwriting and rationalizing socio-ecologically destructive modes of organizing life through subjugation, violence, depletion, and non-reciprocity.
Bibliography Christopher W. Chagnon, Francesco Durante, Barry K. Gills, Sophia E. Hagolani-Albov, Saana Hokkanen, Sohvi M. J. Kangasluoma, Heidi Konttinen, et al.</description></item><item><title>Greenhouse gas emissions</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/greenhouse_gas_emissions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 20:37:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/greenhouse_gas_emissions/</guid><description>tags Climate Scopes Greenhouse gas emissions are often classified in 3 scopes, which roughly correspond to how &amp;ldquo;direct&amp;rdquo; the emission is, or how close is the actual source emitting the gas.
Scope 1 are the direct emissions from combustion of fuel and direct use of fossil fuels.
Scope 2 corresponds to indirect emission from energy usage. This includes any electricity that was produced from a fossil fuel source.
Scope 3 is all the other indirect emissions anywhere in the value chain.</description></item><item><title>AI and climate change</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/ai_and_climate_change/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 20:45:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/ai_and_climate_change/</guid><description>tags Machine learning, Artificial Intelligence, Climate A general-purpose resource: (Dobbe, Whittaker 2019).
A more technical resource with machine learning in mind: (Rolnick et al. 2019).
Bibliography R. Dobbe, M. Whittaker. October 17, 2019. "AI and Climate Change: How They’re Connected, and What We Can Do About It". Medium (blog). October 17, 2019https://medium.com/@AINowInstitute/ai-and-climate-change-how-theyre-connected-and-what-we-can-do-about-it-6aa8d0f5b32c. David Rolnick, Priya L. Donti, Lynn H. Kaack, Kelly Kochanski, Alexandre Lacoste, Kris Sankaran, Andrew Slavin Ross, et al.</description></item><item><title>Kuznets curve</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/kuznets_curve/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 15:52:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/kuznets_curve/</guid><description>tags Climate, Economics From (Henriques, Böhm 2022):
This is based on the work of the U.S. American economist Simon Kuznets who, in the 1950s and 1960s, argued that social inequalities first increase with rising economic growth before decreasing over time (Kuznets&amp;rsquo; 1955).
Kuznets curve for pollution and climate science Bibliography Irene Henriques, Steffen Böhm. May 2022. "The Perils of Ecologically Unequal Exchange: Contesting Rare-earth Mining in Greenland". Journal of Cleaner Production 349 (May):131378.</description></item><item><title>Jevons paradox</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/jevons_paradox/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 08:26:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/jevons_paradox/</guid><description>tags Economics, Climate resources (York, McGee 2016; Polimeni et al. 2015), Wikipedia, Real climate economics blog posts (Jim Barrett) Definition Jevons Paradox is used to describe the situation where an increase in resource efficiency triggered by technological innovation has the counter-intuitive effect of raising the demand and increasing the overall consumption.
It was first described in W. S. Jenvons&amp;rsquo; book The Coal question in 1865.
It is closely to another paradox well known in road planning (Downs–Thomson paradox) and Wirth&amp;rsquo;s law in software engineering.</description></item><item><title>Kaya identity</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/kaya_identity/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 08:24:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/kaya_identity/</guid><description>tags Climate Definition It was developed by Japanese economist Yoichi Kaya.
\(F\) is global CO2 emissions from human sources, \(P\) is global population, \(G\) is GPD, \(E\) is global energy consumption. \[ F = P \times \frac{G}{P} \times \frac{E}{G} \times \frac{F}{E} \]
The fractional terms correspond to well studied quantities:
\(G/P\) is the GDP per capita \(E/G\) is the energy intensity of the GDP \(F/E\) is the carbon footprint of energy Interpretation This identity is simply a rewrite of \(F=F\) in terms of commonly used quantities to highlight several levers one could act on to reduce CO2 emissions.</description></item></channel></rss>