<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Unconventional computing on Hugo Cisneros</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/tags/unconventional-computing/</link><description>Recent content in Unconventional computing on Hugo Cisneros</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 11:41:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugocisneros.com/tags/unconventional-computing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Reservoir computing</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/reservoir_computing/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 11:41:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/reservoir_computing/</guid><description>tags Machine learning, Unconventional computing, Unsupervised learning Reservoir computing is a term used to describe a class of machine learning algorithms that rely on transient dynamics of a dynamical system to implement and manipulate goal-related information.
The most famous example is echo-state networks, which uses random recurrent neural networks as reservoirs, but other dynamical systems can also be used.
Reservoir computing with cellular automata Reservoir computing can use cellular automata as the reservoir.</description></item><item><title>Computing in cellular automata</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/computing_in_cellular_automata/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 17:30:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/computing_in_cellular_automata/</guid><description>tags Unconventional computing, Cellular automata resources (Mitchell 2005; Wolfram 2002) Cellular automata are computational models capable of interesting emergent behavior. A major challenge is to understand which CA rules are doing useful or efficient computations. It is not clear how these systems could be programmed or made to compute a particular function.
Hand-engineered CA rules Below images show CA rules that can compute non trivial functions (Images are from (Wolfram 2002), see A new kind of science online ).</description></item><item><title>Chaos computing</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/chaos_computing/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2020 10:20:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/chaos_computing/</guid><description> tags Unconventional computing</description></item><item><title>Amorphous computing</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/amorphous_computing/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2020 11:12:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/amorphous_computing/</guid><description>tags Unconventional computing papers (Abelson et al. 2000) resources Wikipedia, CSAIL&amp;rsquo;s website From (Abelson et al. 2000):
A colony of cells cooperates to form a multicellular organism under the direction of a genetic program shared by the members of the colony. A swarm of bees cooperates to construct a hive. Humans group together to build towns, cities, and nations.
Amorphous computing was coined by Abelson, Knight, Sussman et al.</description></item></channel></rss>