<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Neural network training on Hugo Cisneros</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/tags/neural-network-training/</link><description>Recent content in Neural network training on Hugo Cisneros</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 09:58:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugocisneros.com/tags/neural-network-training/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Notes on: Network Deconvolution by Ye, C., Evanusa, M., He, H., Mitrokhin, A., Goldstein, T., Yorke, J. A., Fermuller, Cornelia, … (2020)</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/yenetworkdeconvolution2020/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 09:58:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/yenetworkdeconvolution2020/</guid><description>tags Convolutional neural networks, Neural network training source (Ye et al. 2020) Summary This paper introduces so-called Network Deconvolution, advertised as a way to remove pixel-wise and channel-wise correlation in deep neural networks.
The authors base their new operator on the optimal configuration for \(L_2\) linear regression, where gradient descent converges in one single step if and only if:
\[ \frac{1}{N}X^t X = I \] where \(X\) is the feature matrix and \(N\) the number of samples.</description></item><item><title>Double descent</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/double_descent/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2020 18:59:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/double_descent/</guid><description> tags Neural network training</description></item><item><title>The Lottery ticket hypothesis</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/the_lottery_ticket_hypothesis/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 12:42:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/the_lottery_ticket_hypothesis/</guid><description>tags Neural network training resources The AI podcast papers (Frankle and Carbin 2018) When training very large neural networks, the obtained net might have a lot of unused neurons. It is possible, through neural network pruning, to remove a lot of those unused connections to make the overall architecture lighter and faster to run on some hardware.
However, once you have the pruned architecture, it will often not be able to learn anything interesting when it is trained from scratch.</description></item></channel></rss>