<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Economics on Hugo Cisneros</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/tags/economics/</link><description>Recent content in Economics on Hugo Cisneros</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 22:23:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugocisneros.com/tags/economics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Asset economy</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/asset_economy/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 22:23:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/asset_economy/</guid><description> tags Economics books (Adkins et al. 2020) Bibliography Lisa Adkins, Martijn Konings, Melinda Cooper. 2020. The Asset Economy: Property Ownership and the New Logic of Inequality. Medford: Polity Press.</description></item><item><title>Extractivism</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/extractivism/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 21:44:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/extractivism/</guid><description>tags Climate, Economics From (Chagnon et al. 2022), a piece on extractivism as a concept and its relation to globalization:
Extractivism as a concept forms a complex ensemble of self-reinforcing practices, mentalities, and power differentials underwriting and rationalizing socio-ecologically destructive modes of organizing life through subjugation, violence, depletion, and non-reciprocity.
Bibliography Christopher W. Chagnon, Francesco Durante, Barry K. Gills, Sophia E. Hagolani-Albov, Saana Hokkanen, Sohvi M. J.</description></item><item><title>Globalization</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/globalization/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 20:53:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/globalization/</guid><description> tags Economics, Economic liberalism, Complex Systems</description></item><item><title>Gig economy</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/gig_economy/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2022 10:25:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/gig_economy/</guid><description> tags Economics, Economic liberalism Flexible work and exploitation (Chung 2022)
Bibliography Heejung Chung. 2022. The Flexibility Paradox: Why Flexible Working Leads to (self-)exploitation. Bristol: Polity Press.</description></item><item><title>Capitalism</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/capitalism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 20:01:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/capitalism/</guid><description> tags Economics</description></item><item><title>Automation</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/automation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2022 13:01:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/automation/</guid><description> tags Economics, Artificial Intelligence Labor and automation resources Interview with Juan Sebastian Carbonell</description></item><item><title>Kuznets curve</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/kuznets_curve/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 15:52:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/kuznets_curve/</guid><description>tags Climate, Economics From (Henriques, Böhm 2022):
This is based on the work of the U.S. American economist Simon Kuznets who, in the 1950s and 1960s, argued that social inequalities first increase with rising economic growth before decreasing over time (Kuznets' 1955).
Kuznets curve for pollution and climate science Bibliography Irene Henriques, Steffen Böhm. May 2022. "The Perils of Ecologically Unequal Exchange: Contesting Rare-earth Mining in Greenland"</description></item><item><title>Jevons paradox</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/jevons_paradox/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 08:26:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/jevons_paradox/</guid><description>tags Economics, Climate resources (York, McGee 2016; Polimeni et al. 2015), Wikipedia, Real climate economics blog posts (Jim Barrett) Definition Jevons Paradox is used to describe the situation where an increase in resource efficiency triggered by technological innovation has the counter-intuitive effect of raising the demand and increasing the overall consumption.
It was first described in W. S. Jenvons' book The Coal question in 1865.
It is closely to another paradox well known in road planning (Downs–Thomson paradox) and Wirth&amp;rsquo;s law in software engineering.</description></item><item><title>Decentralization</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/decentralization/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 11:12:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/decentralization/</guid><description> tags Economics</description></item><item><title>Economic liberalism</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/economic_liberalism/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2020 10:21:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/economic_liberalism/</guid><description>tags Economics Definition The weekly newspaper The Economist is often described as having economic liberalism among its political alignment.
Decentralization, globalization and economic liberalism Many economic liberalism advocates consider that economic decision should follow some natural tendencies. This, to me, is related to some energy minimization principles where letting everything go normally should lead to the optimal configuration.
In the case of Decentralization, an almost immediate effect is the decrease of prices of some common goods which usually make people happier.</description></item></channel></rss>