<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Economics on Hugo Cisneros</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/tags/economics/</link><description>Recent content in Economics on Hugo Cisneros</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 22:31:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugocisneros.com/tags/economics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Universal basic income</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/universal_basic_income/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2023 22:31:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/universal_basic_income/</guid><description>tags Economics, Economic liberalism Definition Haagh defines UBI as the desire to ‘give all residents a modest regular income grant that is not dependent on means-tests or work-requirements’ (Haagh 2019).
Some critics of UBI In (Harris 2023), the author argues that rather than disrupting capitalism, UBI implementations risk reinforcing the modalities of thought that neoliberalism uses to govern.
Bibliography Louise Haagh. 2019. The Case for Universal Basic Income. The Case for.</description></item><item><title>Automation</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/automation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 08:05:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/automation/</guid><description> tags Economics, Artificial Intelligence Labor and automation resources Interview with Juan Sebastian Carbonell, Interview with Aaron Benanav</description></item><item><title>Gig economy</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/gig_economy/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 15:50:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/gig_economy/</guid><description> tags Economics, Economic liberalism Flexible work and exploitation (Chung 2022)
Gig economy and unions (Gray 2022)
Bibliography Heejung Chung. 2022. The Flexibility Paradox: Why Flexible Working Leads to (self-)exploitation. Bristol: Polity Press. Paul Christopher Gray. 2022. ""the Same Tools Work Everywhere": Organizing Gig Workers with Foodsters United". Labour / Le Travail 90 (1). The Canadian Committee on Labour History:41–84. https://muse.jhu.edu/pub/151/article/870057.</description></item><item><title>Resource curse</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/resource_curse/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2022 15:08:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/resource_curse/</guid><description>tags Economics Definition The resource curse is a phenomenon in which countries with an abundance of natural resources, such as oil, minerals, and other raw materials, often end up with slower economic growth and less democratic governments than countries without such resources. This may be because the wealth generated by the exploitation of these resources is not distributed evenly and can lead to corruption, conflict, and social unrest. The resource curse is also referred to as the &amp;ldquo;paradox of plenty&amp;rdquo;.</description></item><item><title>Dutch disease</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/dutch_disease/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2022 14:54:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/dutch_disease/</guid><description>tags Economics resources Wikipedia Definition From (Corden 1984):
The term Dutch Disease refers to the adverse effects on Dutch manufacturing of the natural gas discoveries of the nineteen sixties, essentially through the subsequent appreciation of the Dutch real exchange rate [footnote]. [footnote] The first printed reference to the term I have found is in the article &amp;ldquo;The Dutch Disease&amp;rdquo; in The Economist November 26th 1977, pp. 82-3.
After the discovery of this large natural gas field in 1959, the Dutch currency became stronger compared to other nations thanks to increased exports.</description></item><item><title>Neoliberalism</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/neoliberalism/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2022 08:35:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/neoliberalism/</guid><description>tags Economics, Economic liberalism Definition In (Hay 2004), the author gives the following definition of neoliberalism;
Economic neoliberalism, I suggest, can be defined in terms of the following traits:
A confidence in the market as an efficient mechanism for the allocation of scarce resources. A belief in the desirability of a global regime of free trade and free capital mobility. A belief in the desirability, all things being equal, of a limited and non-interventionist role for the state and of the state as a facilitator and custodian rather than a substitute for market mechanisms.</description></item><item><title>Finance</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/finance/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 19:01:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/finance/</guid><description> tags Economics</description></item><item><title>Futures contracts</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/futures_contracts/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 16:29:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/futures_contracts/</guid><description> tags Finance, Economics</description></item><item><title>Snake in the tunnel</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/snake_in_the_tunnel/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 16:21:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/snake_in_the_tunnel/</guid><description> tags Economics, Europe resources Wikipedia</description></item><item><title>Land-value tax</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/land_value_tax/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 13:25:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/land_value_tax/</guid><description> tags Economics, Taxation resources Wikipedia</description></item><item><title>Taxation</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/taxation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 13:20:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/taxation/</guid><description> tags Economics</description></item><item><title>Asset economy</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/asset_economy/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 22:23:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/asset_economy/</guid><description> tags Economics books (Adkins et al. 2020) Bibliography Lisa Adkins, Martijn Konings, Melinda Cooper. 2020. The Asset Economy: Property Ownership and the New Logic of Inequality. Medford: Polity Press.</description></item><item><title>Extractivism</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/extractivism/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 21:44:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/extractivism/</guid><description>tags Climate, Economics From (Chagnon et al. 2022), a piece on extractivism as a concept and its relation to globalization:
Extractivism as a concept forms a complex ensemble of self-reinforcing practices, mentalities, and power differentials underwriting and rationalizing socio-ecologically destructive modes of organizing life through subjugation, violence, depletion, and non-reciprocity.
Bibliography Christopher W. Chagnon, Francesco Durante, Barry K. Gills, Sophia E. Hagolani-Albov, Saana Hokkanen, Sohvi M. J. Kangasluoma, Heidi Konttinen, et al.</description></item><item><title>Globalization</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/globalization/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 20:53:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/globalization/</guid><description> tags Economics, Economic liberalism, Complex Systems</description></item><item><title>Capitalism</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/capitalism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 20:01:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/capitalism/</guid><description> tags Economics</description></item><item><title>Kuznets curve</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/kuznets_curve/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 15:52:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/kuznets_curve/</guid><description>tags Climate, Economics From (Henriques, Böhm 2022):
This is based on the work of the U.S. American economist Simon Kuznets who, in the 1950s and 1960s, argued that social inequalities first increase with rising economic growth before decreasing over time (Kuznets&amp;rsquo; 1955).
Kuznets curve for pollution and climate science Bibliography Irene Henriques, Steffen Böhm. May 2022. "The Perils of Ecologically Unequal Exchange: Contesting Rare-earth Mining in Greenland". Journal of Cleaner Production 349 (May):131378.</description></item><item><title>Jevons paradox</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/jevons_paradox/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 08:26:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/jevons_paradox/</guid><description>tags Economics, Climate resources (York, McGee 2016; Polimeni et al. 2015), Wikipedia, Real climate economics blog posts (Jim Barrett) Definition Jevons Paradox is used to describe the situation where an increase in resource efficiency triggered by technological innovation has the counter-intuitive effect of raising the demand and increasing the overall consumption.
It was first described in W. S. Jenvons&amp;rsquo; book The Coal question in 1865.
It is closely to another paradox well known in road planning (Downs–Thomson paradox) and Wirth&amp;rsquo;s law in software engineering.</description></item><item><title>Decentralization</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/decentralization/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 11:12:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/decentralization/</guid><description> tags Economics</description></item><item><title>Economic liberalism</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/economic_liberalism/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2020 10:21:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/economic_liberalism/</guid><description>tags Economics Definition The weekly newspaper The Economist is often described as having economic liberalism among its political alignment.
Decentralization, globalization and economic liberalism Many economic liberalism advocates consider that economic decision should follow some natural tendencies. This, to me, is related to some energy minimization principles where letting everything go normally should lead to the optimal configuration.
In the case of Decentralization, an almost immediate effect is the decrease of prices of some common goods which usually make people happier.</description></item></channel></rss>