<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Economics on Hugo Cisneros</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/tags/economics/</link><description>Recent content in Economics on Hugo Cisneros</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 08:26:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugocisneros.com/tags/economics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Jevons paradox</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/jevons_paradox/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 08:26:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/jevons_paradox/</guid><description>tags Economics, Climate resources (York and McGee 2016; Polimeni et al. 2015), Wikipedia, Real climate economics blog posts (Jim Barrett) Definition Jevons Paradox is used to describe the situation where an increase in resource efficiency triggered by technological innovation has the counter-intuitive effect of raising the demand and increasing the overall consumption.
It was first described in W. S. Jenvons' book The Coal question in 1865.
It is closely to another paradox well known in road planning (Downs–Thomson paradox) and Wirth&amp;rsquo;s law in software engineering.</description></item><item><title>Decentralization</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/decentralization/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2020 11:12:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/decentralization/</guid><description> tags Economics</description></item><item><title>Economic liberalism</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/economic_liberalism/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2020 10:21:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/economic_liberalism/</guid><description>tags Economics Definition The weekly newspaper The Economist is often described as having economic liberalism among its political alignment.
Decentralization, globalization and economic liberalism Many economic liberalism advocates consider that economic decision should follow some natural tendencies. This, to me, is related to some energy minimization principles where letting everything go normally should lead to the optimal configuration.
In the case of Decentralization, an almost immediate effect is the decrease of prices of some common goods which usually make people happier.</description></item></channel></rss>