<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Complex Systems on Hugo Cisneros</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/tags/complex-systems/</link><description>Recent content in Complex Systems on Hugo Cisneros</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 10:25:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugocisneros.com/tags/complex-systems/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Ising model</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/ising_model/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2022 10:25:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/ising_model/</guid><description>tags Complex Systems, Physics Simulation of an Ising model by a cellular automaton Several works have proposed and later refined cellular automaton-base algorithms of Ising models. (Vichniac 1984; Herrmann 1986; Ottavi, Parodi 1989)
Bibliography Gérard Y. Vichniac. January 1, 1984. "Simulating Physics with Cellular Automata". Physica D: Nonlinear Phenomena 10 (1):96–116. DOI. H. J. Herrmann. October 1, 1986. "Fast Algorithm for the Simulation of Ising Models". Journal of Statistical Physics 45 (1):145–51.</description></item><item><title>Climate</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/climate/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2022 09:57:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/climate/</guid><description>tags Complex Systems International environmental agreements From (Pouw et al. 2022):
First, at the international level, universal coalitions are more cost-efficient and effective than fragmented regimes, but more difficult to negotiate and less stable. Second, in developing countries, there is need for substantial external funding to cover the short-run costs of environmental compliance. Third, mar- ket-based solutions have been increasingly applied in international agreements but with mixed results.</description></item><item><title>Christopher Langton</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/christopher_langton/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2022 14:15:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/christopher_langton/</guid><description>tags Artificial life, Complex Systems He is a researcher in the field of artificial life and complex systems. He developed many tools and systems that the Alife community still uses today.
He studied many interesting properties of cellular automata, including the influence of the \(\lambda\) parameter on the chaotic behavior of these CA. A phase transition occurs for certain values of \(\lambda\), which was coined the edge of Chaos (Langton 1990).</description></item><item><title>Boolean networks</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/boolean_networks/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2021 14:46:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/boolean_networks/</guid><description>tags Complex Systems A generalization of Cellular automata Boolean networks could be seen as CA generalization with any topology (not necessarily 1D or 2D). In the standard model, each node of the network is assigned a rule randomly chosen from the \(2^{2^k}\) possible ones with K inputs.
Like for cellular automata, cells (or nodes) don&amp;rsquo;t have to be in just two states (although the name Boolean no longer holds) and updates can be done either synchronously or asynchronously.</description></item><item><title>Notes on: A model of urban evolution based on innovation diffusion by Raimbault, J. (2020)</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/raimbaultmodelurbanevolution2020/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 09:58:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/raimbaultmodelurbanevolution2020/</guid><description>source (Raimbault 2020) tags ALife 2020, Complex Systems, Evolution, Urban science Summary This paper studies the concept of innovation diffusion and how this could be seen as a way cities evolve.
Modeling this enables finding that global integration of cities (fully connected city graph on a territory) is not optimal for efficiently diffusing innovation that can spontaneously appear in any city.
I am interested in taking an ALife inspired approach to studying cities, as it can show cities as they could be.</description></item><item><title>Notes on: Reservoir Computing in Artificial Spin Ice by Jensen, J. H., &amp; Tufte, G. (2020)</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/jensenreservoircomputingartificial2020/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 09:57:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/jensenreservoircomputingartificial2020/</guid><description>source (Jensen, Tufte 2020) tags Reservoir computing, Complex Systems Summary This talk is about artificial spin ice. This model is based on a grid of coupled magnets that can be controlled with a magnetic field. The geometry of that grid can very greatly the kind of behavior one may observe in such systems.
The authors want to use the spin ice model for reservoir computing. They measure useful quantities such as kernel quality \(K\) (ability to separate inputs) and generalization capabilities \(G\) (how similar inputs yield similar results).</description></item><item><title>Notes on: The Architecture of Complexity by Simon, H. A. (1962)</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/simonarchitecturecomplexity1962/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 09:57:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/simonarchitecturecomplexity1962/</guid><description>tags Complexity, Complex Systems source (Simon 1962) Complex systems In such systems, the whole is more than the sum of the parts, not in an ultimate, metaphysical sense, but in the important pragmatic sense that, given the properties of the parts and the laws of their interaction, it is not a trivial matter to infer the properties of the whole. In the face of complexity, an in-principle reductionist may be at the same time a pragmatic holist.</description></item><item><title>Article: Uncertain times</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/article_uncertain_times/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Aug 2020 11:13:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/article_uncertain_times/</guid><description>authors Melanie Mitchell, Jessica Flack source Aeon tags Complex Systems This article is about adopting a complex systems-based view of societal phenomena. All human societies are a collective of individuals with coupled behaviors.
As a result, large-scale society-wide information and local behaviors are coupled. This can be appealing, but also leads to surprising behavior. In complex systems, noise feeding back onto itself can lead to transitions to orderly states.</description></item><item><title>Article: The Cartoon Picture of Magnets That Has Transformed Science</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/the_cartoon_picture_of_magnets_that_has_transformed_science/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Aug 2020 09:18:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/the_cartoon_picture_of_magnets_that_has_transformed_science/</guid><description>tags Ising model, Complex Systems source Quanta magazine The Ising model is an example of very simply defined model that makes complex behavior emerge.
Originally introduced by Wilhelm Lenz and his graduate student Ernst Ising, its purpose was to understand why magnets lose their attractive power when heated past a certain temperature. The model was first tried in 1D, where it fails to show that a magnet stays magnetized, and therefore abandoned.</description></item><item><title>NK model</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/nk_model/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 19:57:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/nk_model/</guid><description> tags Complex Systems</description></item><item><title>Santa Fe Institute</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/santa_fe_institute/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Jul 2020 22:31:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/santa_fe_institute/</guid><description> tags Complex Systems, Physics</description></item><item><title>Automated discovery in complex systems</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/automated_discovery_in_complex_systems/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 08:33:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/automated_discovery_in_complex_systems/</guid><description>tags Complex Systems Evolutionary algorithms and CAs Evolutionary algorithms have been used to find Cellular automata rules with specific behavior (Mitchell et al. 1996; Sapin et al. 2003) . The objective is to optimize a fitness function (majority of cells, presence of gliders and periodic patterns, etc.).
Bibliography Melanie Mitchell, Hyde Park Road, Rajarshi Das, P O Box. 1996. "Evolving Cellular Automata with Genetic Algorithms: A Review of Recent Work"</description></item><item><title>Chemical reaction network</title><link>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/chemical_reaction_network/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 08:44:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://hugocisneros.com/notes/chemical_reaction_network/</guid><description> tags Complex Systems</description></item></channel></rss>